Guide to the John Harte Papers WAG.228
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Harte Papers
1973-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harte, John
WAG.228
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
John Harte, as a member of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Local 608 and of Carpenters for a Stronger Union has been striving for democracy within the union structure since 1973. The collection documents Harte's efforts to bring fair practices to the union, and the repercussions he suffered as a result. The collection includes letters, election materials, flyers, court documents and newspaper clippings.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carpenters for a Stronger Union Records (WAG 066).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In October 1973 John Harte brought his first documented complaint against officials of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Local 608. From 1973 through the early 1990s Harte took part in a continuing campaign for fair practices and democracy in the local. Also active within the organization Carpenters for a Stronger Union, he was involved in attempting to restructure the election process in the union, and making hiring books available to rank and file members to view. The way in which union members were placed on jobs was the major issue for Harte, believing that preferential treatment was given to loyalists over dissenters who wanted to see more accountability in the way the union operated. On his behalf, the National Labor Relations Board brought suit against Local 608, and when the union still delayed in letting Harte see the hiring books, another suit for contempt was brought against it. The case between the National Labor Relations Board and Local 608 lasted from 1987 to 1994. In the early 1990s a federal racketeering charge was brought against Local 608 for alleged involvement with the Genovese crime family. In the RICO case John Harte was one of many people to give a deposition about the activities and irregularities of the union.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains the records of John Harte's struggles within the Carpenters Local 608. Letters documenting his attempts to secure information about the job placement practices of the union and legal records for suits files against the local by the National Labor Relations Board are contained in the collection. Also included are copies of testimony by Harte and others relating to the union and organized crime in a RICO suit. Newspaper clippings, election materials, flyers and publications relating to the union and to the activities of Carpenters for a Stronger Union are also collected.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically. The collection is organized into 1 series:
Missing Title
Series I: Subject Files, 1973-1995.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Harte, 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2003.019.
Testimonies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Decisions.; Depositions.; Fliers (printed matter); Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (State); Labor unions -- Elections -- United States.; Carpenters -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; McGuinness, Paschal; United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America; Forde, Martin; O'Connor, John F.; Carpenters for a Stronger Union (Organization); Harte, John
- Series I: Subject Files, 1973-1995.
  - Carpenters for a Stronger Union: Rusty Nail (bulletin), On the Level (bulletin), Flyers, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Local 608 (John Harte, Paschal McGuinnes, Martin Forde, Patrick Harvey, John O'Connor, Genovese Family), 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Election Materials and United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Local 608 By-Laws and Constitution, 1982-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Harte, John v. John F. O'Connor, Paul Sullivan and Paschal McGuinness: Complaint, Oct 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Martin, Lynn, Secretary of Labor v. United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Complaint (Election Irregularities), Sep 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: John Harte Correspondence, Feb 1987-Jan 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: John Harte Correspondence and Subpoena, Sep 1992-Apr 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: John Harte Deposition, Apr 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: John Harte Testimony (I), Apr 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: John Harte Testimony (II), Apr 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Respondent's Contentions, Jun 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Post-Trial Brief, Oct 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Decision, Oct 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Labor Relations Board v. Carpenters Local 608 United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Report and Recommendations of Special Master, Oct 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - United States v. District Council of New York City and Vicinity of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, et al.: Statements and Testimonies of Carmine Pistone, John F. O'Connor, Vincent Carfaro and Marcello Svedese, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - United States v. District Council of New York City and Vicinity of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, et al.: John Harte Deposition and Subpoena, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)